Guide to the New-York Historical Society Management Committee Records 1804-1938 NYHS-RG 1
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Official Papers, 1805-1938; 10.6 Linear feet
  - Official Papers. 1828 (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Among other matters, this and the next three folders include a substantial number of documents concerning the work of the committee charged with resolving the claims of N-YHS's various creditors, among them being John Pintard and John Francis. Some of the documents submitted by the claimants in 1828 refer to transactions dating from as early as 1809. This first folder also includes a list of the N-YHS Cabinet objects left in rooms with the Lyceum.
  - Official Papers. 1828 (2 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1828 (3 of 5), 1824, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This folder includes the releases negotiated with N-YHS's creditors: NY Evening Post, NY Daily Advertiser, NY American, David Hosack, William Mercein, John Francis, and George Gibbs. There are also unresolved claims from the estate of James Eastburn.
  - Official Papers. 1828 (4 of 5), 1817-1819, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes the claims of John Pintard, the underlying transaction documents from 1809-1819, and the committee's analysis of the claims. Transactions include those associated with creating the mineralogy cabinet in 1817.
  - Official Papers. 1828 (5 of 5), 1828-1829 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes the financial summary for 1828 prepared by Treasurer John Delafield showing revenue (dues collected from members, investment income, and the grant received from New York state) and expenses, with the June 1829 certification of the audit committee.
  - Official Papers. 1829 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes a printed N-YHS Constitution and By-Laws, with donor list; New York Assembly print of the report of N-YHS to the Legislature regarding the state's $5,000 grant; and the pamphlet Plan for Promoting Common School Education in Greece, produced by a committee chaired by Albert Gallatin and meeting at the N-YHS.
  - Official Papers. 1829 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes documents related to N-YHS's cataloging of its collection of coins and medals as of 1829, principally those received from the Kunze estate in 1818. These documents underlie N-YHS's 1830 print version of the coin catalogue. Among the documents are a lengthy extract from an 1800 letter from Kunze to Dr. Mitchell in which Kunze describes the collection, the report of the Committee on the Arrangement of the Cabinet, and inventories.
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (1 of 8). Bills Paid in 1830., 1829-1830 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    This folder and the following seven folders primarily include the bills presented to N-YHS for payment in the 1830s. Generally, the bills are grouped in a folder by the year they were paid, though the date range typically indicates the date of the bill, which is often from a prior year. Some bills dated in the 1830s include references to transactions occurring from as far back as 1827.
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (2 of 8). Bills Paid in 1831., 1830-1831 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (3 of 8). Bills Paid in 1832., 1827, 1830-1832 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (4 of 8). Bills Paid in 1833-1836. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (5 of 8). Bills Paid in 1836-1838. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (6 of 8). Bills Paid in 1839., 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (7 of 8). Bills Paid in 1839. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Official Papers. 1830-1839 (8 of 8). Various Receipts. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Includes a list of books auctioned for N-YHS, books exchanged, dues received, and miscellaneous receipts and financial notes. The bulk of the items are from 1839, but there is one 1830 receipt for dues paid by Dr. Francis.
  - Official Papers. 1839. Washington Inauguration Anniversary Festival. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Official Papers. 1839-1842 (1 of 2). (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes the memorial of Timothy Alden. See also the 1843 folder below for a print advertisement for the 1841 lecture series to be delivered by Jared Sparks.
  - Official Papers. 1839-1842 (2 of 2). Eagle Fire Co. Insurance Policies. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Official Papers. 1843., 1841, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Official Papers. 1844-1845 (1 of 4)., 1844-ca. 1845 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes three designs for a N-YHS medal.
  - Official Papers. 1844-1845 (2 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes the report of the committee charged with considering whether a more appropriate name than "United States of America" might be recommended for the nation; they offer "Republic of Allegania." Includes an article from a German publication about the Collections of the New-York Historical Society, 2nd series, Volume 1; article is in German, with a translation.
  - Official Papers. 1844-1845 (3 of 4). 40th Anniversary Dinner. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1844-1845 (4 of 4). Bills and Accounts., 1841, 1844-1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1846 (1 of 6). (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes the mailing to corresponding members requesting that they obtain and contribute materials for the Library and the N-YHS petition to the U.S. House of Representatives to remove import duties on books.
  - Official Papers. 1846 (2 of 6). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1846 (3 of 6)., 1845-[1846] (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes the Librarian's report concerning the proposed Vattemare donation and the statement by Thomas Henenden(?) opposing the proposed resolution memorializing former U.S. president Andrew Jackson.
  - Official Papers. 1846 (4 of 6). Revival of Lapsed Incorporation., 1846 ca. February (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1846 (5 of 6). Committee on Publishing of Proceedings., 1846 February (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1846 (6 of 6). Inventory of William L. Stone Collection., 1846 April (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1847 (1 of 5). (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Includes committee reports concerning appeals for subscriptions to construct a fireproof building, with drafts of the appeal. Includes the memorial of Peter G. Stuyvesant, written by Luther Bradish.
  - Official Papers. 1847 (2 of 5). (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1847 (3 of 5). (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1847 (4 of 5). Committee on Publishing a Monthly Bulletin of Proceedings. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1847 (5 of 5). Bills and Accounts. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Includes account summaries of transactions dating back to 1845. Most of these relate to the Library General Account and so identify purchased books and other items for 1845-46.
  - Official Papers. 1848 (1 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Official Papers. 1848 (2 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Includes copies of the print appeal for funds for a fireproof building, with handwritten draft of the covering letter.
  - Official Papers. 1848 (3 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Official Papers. 1848 (4 of 4). Bills and Accounts., 1848-1849 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Official Papers. 1848. "Memoranda Relating to the Business of the Hist. Society.", 1848-1862 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    This folder includes a notebook that appears to have been started in 1848 and that includes entries and loose receipts and other documents to 1862, although there are not entries for every year in that range. Entries include lists of life members to 1848, list of tea and coffee furniture held by N-YHS in 1848, inventory of N-YHS publications on hand to 1850, publications sent to other Societies in 1848-1850, list of delinquents receiving the May 1, 1848, and February 1, 1849, circulars, member accounts given to Peter Jackson for collection in 1848 and 1849, expense summaries and distribution record of the 1859 catalogue, and various accounts with entries from 1848 to 1862.
  - Official Papers. 1849 (1 of 4). (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes the report of the committee formed to consider the proposal from the Lyceum of Natural History for an exchange of objects found in the former Cabinet of the N-YHS for books; in considering this proposal, the committee briefly recounts the history of the Lyceum's acquisition of objects from N-YHS.
  - Official Papers. 1849 (2 of 4). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1849 (3 of 4). (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Includes the memorial of Albert Gallatin.
  - Official Papers. 1849 (4 of 4). Bills and Accounts., 1847-1849 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes documents from 1847-1849 concerning bill payment disputes with William Van Norden, printer of the Proceedings; see also the 1848 folder of bills and accounts for Van Norden documents.
  - Official Papers. Circa 1840s. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Includes undated documents, possibly from the 1840s. These include a report from the Librarian proposing new regulations, member nominations, the print version of the request of members to pay any of their dues in arrears, and various financial-related notes.
  - Official Papers. 1850 (1 of 5). (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Includes a draft of the by-laws for the Committee, or Trustees, of the Building Fund. Includes resolutions providing for some financial compensation for the Librarian.
  - Official Papers. 1850 (2 of 5)., 1850 June, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Includes Luther Bradish's remarks regarding James Lenox and his presentation to N-YHS of a copy of Washington's Farewell Address. Includes newspaper clippings from 1852 about the authorship of the Address.
  - Official Papers. 1850 (3 of 5). (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes resolutions concerning the death of U.S. President Zachary Taylor.
  - Official Papers. 1850 (4 of 5). (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1850 (5 of 5). (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1851 (1 of 6). (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Official Papers. 1851 (2 of 6). (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1851 (3 of 6). (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1851 (4 of 6). (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Includes the memorial to Philip Hone.
  - Official Papers. 1851 (5 of 6). (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes newspaper clippings related to meetings, such as announcements, record of proceedings, remarks, etc.
  - Official Papers. 1851 (6 of 6). Bills and Accounts., 1847-1855 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    The original label for these documents indicates that they are for Librarian George H. Moore's account for the years 1850-51. The documents date from 1847-1955, with some account lists referring to transactions back to 1845.
  - Official Papers. 1852 (1 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1852 (2 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes the records of ticket distribution for the Daniel Webster lecture of February 1852 and minutes of the committee making the arrangements.
  - Official Papers. 1852 (3 of 4). Building Fund., 1851-1852 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes documents related to the efforts to raise subscriptions for a fireproof building fund. These documents include a print version of John Jay's objections to the building fund trustees' intent to purchase property before certain conditions were met, a renewal of the subscription appeal, the circular announcing a series of benefit lectures, and a ticket to the series.
  - Official Papers. 1852 (4 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1853. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1854 (1 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1854 (2 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1855 (1 of 3). (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Includes correspondence from Benson Lossing regarding New York state government manuscripts he has found from the colonial and early republic periods, and the report of the N-YHS committee formed to look into these.
  - Official Papers. 1855 (2 of 3). (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1855 (3 of 3). Building Fund. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1856 (1 of 4)., 1855-1856 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Includes the report and memorial of the Committee on National Medals (formed in April 1854), with related response from the U.S. Mint. Includes records of dues in arrears and some related correspondence from former members declining to pay.
  - Official Papers. 1856 (2 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1856 (3 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1856 (4 of 4). Building Fund. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1857 (1 of 3). (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes the report of the Fine Arts Committee recommending acceptance of the donation by John Earl Williams of a bust of Columbus.
  - Official Papers. 1857 (2 of 3). (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes President Bradish's remarks at the November 3 dedication of the new N-YHS building and a ticket to the event, Chairman of the Building Fund Trustees de Peyster's draft remarks at the December meeting, and the final report of the Buildings Committee.
  - Official Papers. 1857 (3 of 3). (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1858 (1 of 7). (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1858 (2 of 7). (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1858 (3 of 7). (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1858 (4 of 7). Letter Concerning Steam Power., 1858 January 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Includes Joseph Renwick's lengthy letter to Frederic de Peyster proposing a paper to be read to N-YHS regarding steam power. In the letter, among other topics, Renwick discusses his own experience aboard Fulton's original steamboat on the Hudson and other such experiences.
  - Official Papers. 1858 (5 of 7). Columbia College Rental., 1858 May (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Includes documents related to the rental of the N-YHS Library to Columbia College for university lectures.
  - Official Papers. 1858 (6 of 7). NY Gallery of Fine Arts., 1858 June (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Includes documents related to the acquisition of the collection of the New York Gallery of the Fine Arts, including the signed and sealed agreement, which includes a list of the paintings and sculpture acquired.
  - Official Papers. 1858 (7 of 7)., 1858-1859 (Box OS-1, Folder 7)
    Includes a recapitulation of the expenses and receipts (1850-1859) associated with the Building Fund.
  - Volume: By-Laws, Report on Seth Grosvenor's Will, New-York Gallery of the Fine Arts Agreement and Catalogue, Lectures, 1858 (Volume RG1.32, Folder -)
    Includes transcribed copies of the noted documents. Lectures refers to the report of the committee on lectures for 1958. Volume was bound by N-YHS on July 2, 1936.
  - Official Papers. 1859 (1 of 4). (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1859 (2 of 4). (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Includes the agreement between N-YHS and the Second Universalist Society for the rental of rooms for services, with provision to extend the agreement to 1862; later pencilled annotations indicate the possibility of extending the term to 1866.
  - Official Papers. 1859 (3 of 4). (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1859 (4 of 4). Ventilation Report., 1859 May (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Includes a report by Dr. D.B. Reid assessing the ventilation of the N-YHS building.
  - Official Papers. 1860 (1 of 6). (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Includes the memorial of James Kirke Paulding.
  - Official Papers. 1860 (2 of 6). (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Includes a circular to members with information concerning meetings, library hours, collections, publications, etc.
  - Official Papers. 1860 (3 of 6). (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Includes the report of the committee appointed to attempt to acquire the manuscripts owned by Abraham Tomlinson.
  - Official Papers. 1860 (4 of 6). (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1860 (5 of 6). Washington Irving Birthday Commemoration., 1860 March-April (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Includes an event invitation and ticket, correspondence, draft circular announcement, N-YHS President Bradish's remarks at the event, annotated clippings of William Cullen Bryant's remarks, and the report of the N-YHS Committee on Arrangements.
  - Official Papers. 1860 (6 of 6). O'Reilly's Telegraph Documents. Draft Catalogue., 1860 May (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1861 (1 of 3). (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Includes the report of the committee formed to draft regulations for admission to the N-YHS meetings and its collections.
  - Official Papers. 1861 (2 of 3). (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Includes memorial of John W. Francis.
  - Official Papers. 1861 (3 of 3). (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1862 (1 of 4). (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1862 (2 of 4). (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Includes member and non-member tickets for entrance to the March meeting.
  - Official Papers. 1862 (3 of 4). (Box 7, Folder 10)
    The member nominations in this folder include that of Henry Dexter (October).
  - Official Papers. 1862 (4 of 4). (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Official Papers. 1863 (1 of 6). (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Includes the memorial of Edward Robinson.
  - Official Papers. 1863 (2 of 6). (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1863 (3 of 6). (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1863 (4 of 6). (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1863 (5 of 6). Luther Bradish Memorials. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1863 (6 of 6). William Bradford Birthday Commemoration. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    N-YHS petty cash expenditures are recorded on the back of tickets for the Bradford event. See also 1864 folders for similar petty cash records for that year on the back of Bradford tickets.
  - Official Papers. 1864 (1 of 8)., 1863-1864 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Includes the rules established in January for the Executive Committee.
  - Official Papers. 1864 (2 of 8). (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Includes documents related to the Jarvis and Thomas J. Bryan art collections.
  - Official Papers. 1864 (3 of 8). (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Includes the committee report related to the Jarvis and Bryan art collections. Includes the circular requesting contributions of arms, trophies, and other artifacts related to the U.S. army and navy, especially New York City regimental flags and captured rebel flags. Includes documents related to the commemoration of the 200th anniversary of the conquest of New Netherland.
  - Official Papers. 1864 (4 of 8). (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1864 (5 of 8). Petty Cash Records. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1864 (6 of 8). Spooner Dictionary Matter. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Includes the agreement between N-YHS and bookseller James Bonton for the use of N-YHS's stereograph plates to print new editions of two works by Spooner, the subsequent cancellation of the agreement and transferral of the ownership of the plates to Bonton, and the correspondence from Bonton concerning missing plates that related to these matters.
  - Official Papers. 1864 (7 of 8). Lectures on Egypt. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Includes mostly financial bills and receipts related to the lecture series.
  - Official Papers. 1864 (8 of 8). E.H. Davis Collection., 1861, 1863-1864 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Includes the signed agreement, inventory, and correspondence concerning the acquisition of Edwin Hamilton Davis's collection of American antiquities.
  - Official Papers. 1865 (1 of 4). (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Includes a sketch "Waiting for the Returns--Annual Election NYHS," drawn by Domestic Corresponding Secretary Brodhead at the January meeting.
  - Official Papers. 1865 (2 of 4). (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1865 (3 of 4). (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Includes the report of the committee on arms, trophies, and other U.S. army and navy artifacts.
  - Official Papers. 1865 (4 of 4). Committee on the Publication Fund., 1865-1866 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    Includes the Committee on the Publication Fund report of November 7, 1865, and the minutes of the committee meetings for March 18, 1865, to March 17, 1866.
  - Official Papers. 1866 (1 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Includes the letter from Mathew Brady of January 6, 1866, in which he proposes a conditional donation of his collection of photographs to N-YHS.
  - Official Papers. 1866 (2 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Includes documents concerning complaints about the cold winter temperature in the library, and its resolution.
  - Official Papers. 1866 (3 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Includes an unsigned agreement to rent the N-YHS hall to the Second Universalist Society for 1866-67, with pencilled revisions to rent it to the Reformed Presbyterian Church for 1867-68.
  - Official Papers. 1866 (4 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Includes the memorial of Horace Green.
  - Official Papers. Circa 1864-1866. De Peyster Matters. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Includes various documents that appear to have been compiled by, or relate in some way to, N-YHS President Frederic De Peyster. These include records of the distribution, expenses and receipts associated with various addresses by De Peyster (ca. 1865-1866 and perhaps to 1868); historical observations sent to De Peyster by John McVicker(?); information from the Department of Charities and Correction on the number of people in its various institutions and receiving "outdoor" aid (1864); a letter from the New York City Inspector's Department responding to De Peyster that fears of the draft have prevented the taking of an accurate city census and so can only provide estimates for 1863-64 (1865); historical notes on some N-YHS presidents; a print of a speech made in Congress on April 11, 1864, by H. Winter Davis of Maryland, sent by Davis to De Peyster; appeals from the Ladies' Mount Vernon Association for contributions; and a clipping regarding remarks at N-YHS, including those of De Peyster and George Bancroft memorializing Edward Everett.
  - Official Papers. 1867 (1 of 5)., 1867-1868 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1867 (2 of 5). (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Includes a signed agreement between N-YHS and the Second Reformed Presbyterian Church for rental of the hall for services for 1867-68.
  - Official Papers. 1867 (3 of 5). (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Includes the memorial of John Alsop King.
  - Official Papers. 1867 (4 of 5). (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1867 (5 of 5). Plaster Bas-Relief by Ottin., 1855, 1867 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Includes documents related to the acquisition of Ottin's bas-relief Triumphal March of the Republic. Two documents, including one signed by Monsieur Ottin, are in French.
  - Official Papers. 1867-1868. Sales of Osgood's Discourse. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Includes bills and other financial records related to the sales of a print of a discourse by Samuel Osgood.
  - Official Papers. 1868 (1 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1868 (2 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Includes Librarian Moore's reflections on the history of his compensation since 1849 as the subject is on the April agenda; the related committee report is also in the folder. The folder also includes the N-YHS circular requesting support for creating the Museum of History, Antiquities, and Art in Central Park.
  - Official Papers. 1868 (3 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1868 (4 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Includes unattributed remarks proposing an increase in membership dues in order to support current, operational expenses.
  - Official Papers. 1869 (1 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Official Papers. 1869 (2 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Includes the memorials of George Folsom and Alexander Stevens. Includes the report of the committee assigned to evaluate Thomas Townsend's Historical Record & Encyclopedia of the Great Rebellion to determine whether to acquire it; see also the next folder for other documents on this subject, including Townsend's comments to the Executive Committee about his work.
  - Official Papers. 1869 (3 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Official Papers. 1869 (4 of 4). (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Official Papers. 1870 (1 of 4). (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes the memorial of Gulian C. Verplanck.
  - Official Papers. 1870 (2 of 4). (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Includes the memorial of Frederick S. Cozzens.
  - Official Papers. 1870 (3 of 4). (Box 10, Folder 3)